Medical illustrations for Harvey Cushing by Mildred Codding and others
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Medical illustrations for Harvey Cushing by Mildred Codding and others
1912-1938
Ms Coll 60
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
4
This collection contains illustrations (both early sketches and proofs) done for Harvey Cushing, as well as notes, correspondence, photographic reprints, and other materials relating to the production of Cushing and Eisenhardt's 1938 monograph Meningiomas. The majority of the illustrations were done by Mildred Codding, who was Cushing's illustrator from 1929 until his retirement in 1932. Several illustrations by others, including M. Warner, are also included in this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection is comprised of materials from three separate gifts to the Historical Library, donated by Gloria Robinson (2012) and Dorothy Robinson (2017) from the collection of Dr. Franklin Robinson, and by Michael Hand from the estate of his sister, Rosalie Marie Hand (2013).
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series: I. Proofs from Meningiomas by Codding. II. Notes and other materials relating to Meningiomas. III. Illustrations from other publications by Codding. IV. Illustrations for Harvey Cushing by others.
Biographical / Historical
Mildred Codding (1902-1991) was the medical illustrator for Dr. Harvey Cushing from 1929 until his retirement in 1932. Her illustrations feature prominently in many of Dr. Cushing's publications, including his 1938 monograph Meningiomas.
A native of Somerville, Massachusetts, Codding graduated from Wellesley College in 1924 and earned a master's degree in zoology from Columbia University in 1926. In 1928, she began to train as a medical illustrator at Johns Hopkins University under Dr. Max Brödel, the pioneer of the "carbon dust" technique commonly used in 20th century medical and scientific illustrations. After just one year of study, Codding was selected to begin part-time work with Dr. Cushing in 1929. In a later interview, Codding stated that Cushing, who was a talented illustrator in his own right and highly particular in general, "was not easy to illustrate for."
After Cushing's retirement to Yale University in 1933, Codding stayed on at the Brigham Hospital in Boston, where she did operative photography for Dr. John Homans and Dr. David Cheever. She resumed drawing with Dr. Elliott Cutler and Dr. Robert Zollinger, providing the illustrations for their Atlas of Surgical Operations, published in 1939. Codding's next major work was the Atlas of Pelvic Operations, published in 1953 by Dr. Langdon Parsons and Dr. Howard Ulfelder of Massachusetts General Hospital. Later, she worked with Dr. Donald Matson and Dr. John Shillito of the Brigham and Children's Hospitals, illustrating pediatric neurosurgical operations. Codding left the Brigham in 1968, but continued to work with Dr. Shillito for the next 12 years on his Atlas of Pediatric Neurosurgical Operations, which was published in 1981.
Codding never married and had no close family. In her later years, she retired to Cape Cod, where she enjoyed making watercolor paintings of the scenes around her home. She died on August 3, 1991 at her home in Eastham, Massachusetts.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
- Proofs from Meningiomas by Mildred Codding, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Proofs from Cushing and Eisenhardt's Meningiomas (1938), organized by chapter.
  - Chapter IV - Intraspinal (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Folder contains 3 loose caption labels for Figs. 49, 53, and 54, and 2 proofs mounted on cardboard. One proof is labeled "Emma Hill."
  - Chapter V - Combined Neurinomas and Meningiomas (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Folder contains 2 proofs mounted on cardboard, corresponding to Figs. 66 and 68 in Meningiomas. Fig. 66 is labeled "Goldman" and Fig. 68 is labeled "Dale Harvey."
  - Chapter VI - Multiple Meningiomas (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Folder contains 3 mounted proofs corresponding to Meningiomas Figs. 84, 88, and 92. Figures are labeled in pencil "Edith Mindes I," "Mindes II," and "Mindes III" respectively.
  - Chapter VII - Meningiomas without Dural Attachment (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Folder contains mounted proofs of Meningiomas Figs. 113 and 127. Fig. 113 is labeled in pencil "Montgomery" and "Transverse cleft." Fig. 127 is labeled "Nicholl" and "deep sylvian cleft."
  - Chapter VIII - Cerebellar Chamber: Basilar Groove (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Folder contains 3 mounted proofs corresponding to Meningiomas Figs. 134 and 136. All illustrations pertain to the "Josephine Nilson" case.
  - Chapter IX - Cerebellar Chamber: Subtentorial and Recess (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Folder contains 1 proof, corresponding to Meningiomas Fig. 148. Illustration is labeled "Hanrahan."
  - Chapter X - Cerebellar Chamber: Those Simulating Acoustic Tumors (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Contains 1 proof mounted on cardboard, corresponding to Meningiomas Fig. 158. Proof is labeled "O'Toole."
  - Chapter XII - Suprasellar (Chiasmal Syndrome) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Contains 7 proofs of various sizes mounted on cardboard, corresponding to Meningiomas Figs. 187, 195, 191, and 199A/B/C/D. Illustrations are labeled "Walkden" (187), "Steinberg" (191), and "Jackson" (195). Folder also contains two unmounted illustrations labeled "Anderson" corresponding to Figs. 183 and 184.
  - Chapter XIII - Olfactory Groove (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Contains 2 proofs mounted, corresponding to Meningiomas Figs. 205 and 219. Fig. 205 (labeled "Fig. 4") is an illustration signed by "S.A. Sewell," and caption notes that this image is "Kindness of Prof. Shattuck." Fig. 219 is labeled "Lampman."
  - Chapter XV - Sphenoidal Ridge: Deep or Clinoidal Third (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Folder contains 2 proofs mounted on cardboard, corresponding to Meningiomas Figs. 239 and 249. Fig 239. is labeled "Hultin" and Fig. 249 is labeled "Mutter."
  - Chapter XVI - Sphenoidal Ridge: Middle (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Contains 2 mounted proofs corresponding to Meningiomas Figs. 270 (unlabeled) and 274. Fig. 270 is labeled "Mary Partridge" and 274 is labeled "Furtado."
  - Chapter XVII - Sphenoidal Ridge: Hyperostosing (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Contains 1 mounted proof, corresponding to Meningiomas Fig. 309. Illustration is labeled "Theriault."
  - Chapter XX - Parasagittal: Global (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Contains 3 proofs mounted on cardboard, corresponding to Meningiomas Figs. 343 (labeled on back in pencil), 372, and 373. Fig. 343 is "Doucette," Fig. 372 is "Parkhurst," and Fig. 373 is "Taylor."
  - Chapter XXIX - Convexity: Parietal (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Contains 1 proof mounted on paper and cardboard, corresponding to Fig. 585. Illustration is labeled "Pryzbos."
  - Miscellaneous proofs by Mildred Codding (Box 1, Folder 15)
    These 5 mounted illustrations by Mildred Codding may have been used in the production of Meningiomas or appear in the monograph, but their exact locations in the text are unknown. Item-level descriptions: small illustration of a tumor in pencil, mounted on 2 layers of cardboard; 4-part illustration, detached from board, with labels reading "Frontal lobe," "Sella turcica," and "calcified area"; mounted illustration labeled "Endicott," "glio-chias." (?), "Fig. 16 Do not reduce," and on back: "Endicott 13340," "Vol. 8"; mounted illustration of a brain labeled "Anna Simpson," "para," with text on illustration reading "Old bone flap"; mounted illustration, no patient name or identifier, with text on illustration reading "Chiasma," "A. Carotis," "N. Oculomotor."
- Notes and other materials relating to Meningiomas, Series II
  This series contains notes, correspondence, photographs, illustrations, and other materials relating to the production of Harvey Cushing's Meningiomas, organized by chapter.
  Although the original folders corresponding to each chapter were heavily disintegrated and are not included in this collection, the labels and any text that appeared on the folders themselves have been included. Materials that were found loose (i.e., not in a folder) have been sorted into the appropriate folders when possible.
  Illustrations by Mildred Codding included in this series pertain to cases discussed in Meningiomas, but the illustrations themselves do not appear in the published monograph.
  - Chapter I - Historical and Terminological & Chapter II - Pathology (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Contains proof of Fig. 4 (photograph) mounted on card; proof of Fig. 5 (photograph, labeled Fig. 7) mounted on paper; proof of Fig. 9 (photograph, labeled Fig. 10) mounted on paper; likely early version of Fig. 10 (illustration, labeled Fig. 12), showing differences from published figure; microscopy photograph labeled "Fig. 9. A cerebral hernia in the process of withdrawal from an arachnoid villus," mounted on paper; 2 detached images: 1 illustration, 1 photograph of a tumor (labeled on back "Fig. 10 Cavendish lecture"); and 2 proof sheets labeled "Fig. 1" and "Fig. 8" showing captions but no images.
  - Chapter IV - Intraspinal (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Contains various handwritten notes in Cushing's handwriting; a card from "The Country Club" with Cushing's handwriting on back; and several typed pages, many pertaining to the Josephine Nilson case.
  - Chapter IX - Cerebellar: Subtentorial and Recess (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Contains 4 mounted illustrations by Mildred Codding pertaining to Chapter IX cases: "Storer" and "Warme." Illustrations do not appear in Meningiomas, but were likely included in an earlier publication and consulted later by Cushing.
  - Chapter XII - Suprasellar (Chiasmal Syndrome) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Contains original label from Suprasellar folder; 5 loose photographic reprints with citations and dates on back; and 1 mounted photographic reprint of "Fig. 1."
  - Chapter XIII - Olfactory Groove (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Contains 8 mounted photographic reprints labeled Figs. 3, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, and "22 & 23." The image labeled "Fig. 14" appears as Fig. 211 in Meningiomas. While other images do not appear in the text, all cases are cited on p. 253. Also contains 13 loose photographic reprints with labels on reverse; illustration (by Codding?) of "Lena Moscowitz" case; loose paper with writing in pencil reading "Fig. 14 used for olf. groove chapter"; and original folder label.
  - Chapter XIV - Intraorbital (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Contains original "Intraorbital" folder label and 1 photographic reprint with citation on reverse.
  - Chapter XVI - Sphenoidal Ridge: Middle (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Contains a letter in French from Dr. Daniel Petit-Dutaillis, originally clipped to 2 photographic reprints of a brain; handwritten notes by Cushing; and 2 mounted illustrations by Codding: "Mary Partridge" and "Sullivan."
  - Chapter XVIII - Sphenoidal Ridge: Sylvian Point (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Contains 1 mounted illustration by Codding, labeled "Sladkiovilno."
  - Chapter XIX - Basilar: Infratemporal (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Contains 2 mounted illustrations by Codding, both labeled "Helen Thomas."
  - Chapter XX - Parasagittal: Global (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Contains front of original folder, showing patient list; loose notes on paper in Cushing's handwriting; and 10 illustrations by Codding: Leonard Wood, Jessie Wall, Charles F. Taylor (3x), McCarthy, Gerding, Mrs. Dain, Vosberg, Jeanie Wiesleder.
  - Chapter XXI - Parasagittal: Hyperostosing (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Folder contains front of original folder showing patient list; loose photographic reprints with citations on reverse; proof (photograph mounted on paper) of Fig. 428; proof (reprint in negative, mounted on paper) of Fig. 376; large sketch (folded) corresponding to Fig. 418 with notes on reverse; sketch corresponding to Fig. 419; correspondence from 1933 to Cushing signed "Robin;" 2 handwritten letters and 2 photographs (labeled "A658" on reverse); additional notes and correspondence; handwritten notes and sketches on card, apparently by Cushing; and an illustration by Codding on paper, consisting of several pieces of paper glued together, labeled "Hyperostosis 55."
  - Chapter XXII - Peritorcular (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Contains original "Peritorcular" folder label; photographic reprint with caption mounted on paper, labeled "James case;" and 3 illustrations by Codding: Erma Kennedy, Frank Hartz, and Woolson.
  - Chapter XXIV - Convexity I (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Contains 1 reprint of illustration by Codding, corresponding to Meningiomas Fig. 505.
  - Chapter XXV - Convexity: Precoronal (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Typed correspondence from S. Forrest Cowell, attached to "Catalogue description of Specimen No. 1454.1 in the Series of General Pathology;" handwritten notes by Cushing; list: "X-rays Frontal group."
  - Chapter XXVI - Convexity: Coronal (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Typed notes, 1 sheet; reprinted illustration by Codding corresponding to Fig. 522; mounted illustration by Codding labeled "Arthur Perlin;" and original Coronal folder label.
  - Chapter XXVII - Convexity: Postcoronal (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Contains 1 reprint of illustration by Codding corresponding to Fig. 534, and 4 mounted illustrations by Codding in ink: Maggie Wyman, Edna Rumney, Charles Goddard (2x).
  - Chapter XXVIII - Convexity: Paracentral (Para-Rolandic) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Contains original folder label, various typed and handwritten notes, and a reprint of a Codding illustration.
  - Convexity: Occipital (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Note that there is no chapter in Meningiomas corresponding to Occipital tumors because Cushing had no recorded cases of tumors of this type; see p. 564 in Meningiomas for discussion. Folder contains handwritten and typed notes, and original folder label.
  - Chapter XXX - Convexity: Temporo-Sylvian (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Contains 3 mounted illustrations by Codding: Martha Caswell (2x) and Julia Jacobs.
  - Differential Diagnosis (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Contains 4 pages of typed notes and original "Differential Diagnoses" folder label, in Cushing's handwriting.
  - "Endothelioma - Misc. MS." (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Original label (included) reads "Endothelioma - Misc. MS." Folder includes: 4 illustrations in pencil, blue pencil, and red ink similar to Meningiomas Fig. 504.; correspondence from E.R. Carpenter, attached to 3 photographs of brains with notes on back; typed copy or notes on yellow and white paper; 12 pages of what appear to be citations in Chinese and German; and handwritten copy on lined paper (not in Cushing's hand).
  - "Misc. notes..." (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Original label (included) reads "Meningiomas - Misc. notes to put with original manuscript, etc. of different chapters." Contains 3 photographic reprints mounted on paper.
  - Fragments relating to Meningiomas (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Contains 3 loose pieces of paper with handwritten notes, found with rest of collection, that could not be classified into folders.
  - Miscellaneous photos relating to Meningiomas (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Loose photographs and reprints relating to Meningiomas that could not be classified into a folder. Three of the photographs are mounted. There is also a letter from K.G. McKenzie to Cushing that was attached to 2 of the photos (labeled N49 on reverse).
- Illustrations from other publications by Codding, Series III
  Arrangement
  Organized chronologically by publication.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Michael Hand, from the estate of Rosalie Marie Hand, 2013.
  - Tumors Arising from the Blood Vessels of the Brain (Cushing and Bailey), 1928 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Full citation: Cushing, H. and Bailey, P. Tumors arising from the blood vessels of the brain: Angiomatous malformations and hemangioblastomas. Springfield, Ill.: Charles C. Thomas, 1928.
    Contains 6 mounted proofs, corresponding to Figs. 5 (O'Laughlin), 60 (Dunn), 61 (Dunn), 91 (McAvoy?), 95 (McAvoy), and 130 (Gorden).
  - "Electro-Surgery as an Aid to the Removal of Intracranial Tumors" (Cushing), 1928 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Full citation: Cushing, H. "Electro-surgery as an aid to the removal of intracranial tumors." With a preliminary note by W.T. Bovie, Ph.D., Chicago. Surg. Gynec. Obstet., Dec. 1928 (47): 751-784.
    Folder contains 8 original illustrations in pencil on paper (unmounted) by Mildred Codding, corresponding to figures appearing in "Electro-surgery."
  - "Meningiomas Arising from the Tuberculum Sellae" (Cushing and Eisenhardt), 1929 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Full citation: Cushing, H. and Eisenhardt, L. "Meningiomas arising from the tuberculum sellae: With the syndrome of primary optic atrophy and bitemporal field defects combined with a normal sella turcica in a middle aged person." Arch Ophthalmol. 1929;1(1):1-41 (Part 1) and 1929;1(2):168-206 (Part 2).
    Folder contains 15 original illustrations in pencil on paper by Mildred Codding. Some are composites of illustrations on multiple sheets of paper glued together; others show multiple drafts of the same or similar illustrations.
  - "Chiasmal Syndrome," Part I (Cushing), 1930 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Full citation: Cushing, H. "The chiasmal syndrome: Of primary optic atrophy and bitemporal field defects in adults with a normal sella turcica." Arch Ophthalmol. 1930;3(5):505-551.
    Folder contains 5 mounted proofs with captions illustrated by Mildred Codding, corresponding to Figs. 35, 40, 44, 45 (two versions), and 46.
  - "Chiasmal Syndrome," Part II (Cushing), 1930 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Full citation: Cushing, H. "The chiasmal syndrome: Of primary optic atrophy and bitemporal field defects in adults with a normal sella turcica." Arch Ophthalmol. 1930;3(6):704-735.
    Folder contains 4 mounted proofs with captions illustrated by Mildred Codding.
  - "Chiasmal Syndrome" sketches, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Folder contains 19 original illustrations in pencil on paper (unmounted) corresponding to various figures appearing in "Chiasmal Syndrome" Parts I and II (1930). Many are labeled with patient names and diagnoses on reverse.
  - Lister Memorial Lecture (Cushing), 1930 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Full citation: Cushing, H. "Neurohypophysial mechanisms from a clinical standpoint." Lancet, July 19, 26, 1930; 2: 119-127 (Part 1); 175-184 (Part 2).
    The Lister Memorial Lecture delivered at the Royal College of Surgeons of England, July 9, 1930.
    Contains 1 page of illustrations in pencil. Images do not appear in the Lancet publication, but may have been presented alongside the Lister Memorial Lecture (see footnote in article).
  - Intracranial Tumors (Cushing), 1932 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Full citation: Cushing, H. Intracranial tumors: Notes upon a series of two thousand verified cases with surgical-mortality percentages pertaining thereto. Springfield, Ill.: Charles C. Thomas, 1932.
    Folder contains 15 illustrations (proofs and sketches) in pencil and pencil and ink by Mildred Codding corresponding to various figures in the 1932 Intracranial Tumors monograph. Final (proof) and early (sketch) versions of Figs. 37, 63, and 91 are included together for comparison.
  - Miscellaneous illustrations by Mildred Codding (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Folder contains 1 proof and 13 sketches in pencil and pencil and ink by Mildred Codding. Many are labeled with patient names and/or diagnoses. The publications associated with these illustrations are unknown.
- Illustrations for Harvey Cushing by others, Series IV
  - Proofs from H. Cushing and L.H. Weed's article in JHH Bulletin, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Full citation: Cushing, H. and Weed, L.H. "Studies on the cerebro-spinal fluid and its pathway, No. IX. Calcareous and osseous deposits in the arachnoidea." Johns Hopk. Hosp. Bull., 1915; 26(297): 367-372. Contains 3 proofs, corresponding to Figs. 7, 8, and 9.
    Illustrations likely by M. Warner.
  - Pathology illustrations by M. Warner, 1910s
    These mounted illustrations of microscopy slides appear to have been illustrated by M. Warner. Although these illustrations do not appear in "Meningiomas," their inclusion in the 2017 Robinson gift indicates that they may have been used in the production of the monograph in some way. Some, but not all, of the names on these illustrations correspond to cases in "Meningiomas."
    - Illustrations of Corbitt (Thomas C.) (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Three illustrations of various sizes mounted on carboard, labeled Fig. 9, 10, and 11.
    - Illustrations of Croy (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Contains 1 mounted illustration labeled "Croy" and signed in pencil by M. Warner.
    - Illustrations of Hardwick (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Contains 3 mounted illustrations by M. Warner labeled "Hardwick."
    - Illustration of McLean (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Contains 1 mounted illustration labeled "McLean H&E."
    - Illustration of Nilson (Josephine) (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Contains 1 mounted illustration labeled "Nilson."
    - Illustration of Pinkney (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Contains 1 mounted illustration labeled "Pinkney."
    - Illustration of Poor (Box 4, Folder 8)
      1 mounted illustration. Cover sheet is labeled "Poor." Image is labeled "Endothelioma of Brain."
    - Illustration of Pumphrey (Agnes) (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Contains 1 mounted illustration labeled "Agnes Pumphrey."
    - Illustration of Riley (Catherine) (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Contains 1 mounted illustration labeled "Catherine Riley."
  - Sketch of mouth on JHH letterhead, likely by Cushing (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Folder contains a sketch of a mouth on Johns Hopkins Hospital letterhead, with notes in Cushing's handwriting. Cushing was known to make post-operative sketches directly on hospital letterhead.
  - Proof from "Chronic Subdural Hematoma" (T.J. Putnam and H. Cushing), 1925 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Contains 1 full-color painting mounted on cardboard, labeled "Fig. 1." Illustrator unknown.